Guide to the Rice University Honor Council records, 1916-2021 UA 221
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Honor Council records
1916-2021
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 221
6.25 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Records of the business of the Rice University Honor Council such as hearings and trial abstracts, as well as documentation of procedural and constitutional revisions.
Biographical / Historical
The Rice Honor System was created by Rice Institute students in 1916. It is comprised of current Rice undergraduate and graduate students. The Council reviews cases and decides appropriate penalties. "The purpose of the Honor System is to allow maximum freedom for students, undergraduate and graduate, in the completion of all academic work and to ensure the integrity of the work. When students accept this freedom and trust, they are placed on their honor by the group neither to cheat on any assignment nor to violate the trust placed in them in any way. Students demonstrate their responsibilities to their fellow students under the Honor System when they can pledge, in good conscience, that their work is their own and that they have neither witnessed nor suspect violations by others." (Article 1 Section 1 of Honor Council constitution, http://honor.blogs.rice.edu/files/2011/03/Constitution-2011.pdf). For more information, see http://honor.rice.edu/.
Scope and Contents
Records of the business of the Rice University Honor Council such as hearings and trail abstracts, as well as documentation of procedural and constitutional revisions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this restricted material requires written permission from the Rice University Dean of Undergraduates Office for undergraduate cases, and the Dean of Graduates and Post-Doctoral Studies for graduate cases.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the Woodson Research Center regularly, beginning in 1998.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); letters (correspondence); memorandums; constitutions
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Honor System booklets, 1921-2005
  - Honor System booklets (Scattered Issues), 1921-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Constitution and related material, 1919-1995
  - Constitution, correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution, 1948, 1952, 1955-1958, ca. 1919, proposed amend. 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Memoranda and Official Notices, 1935-1989
  - Memoranda, Official Notices, 1935-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Hearings and Trials abstracts, 1976-2007
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2000-2001 (Box 2a, Folder 12)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2001-2002 (Box 2a, Folder 13)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2002-2003 (Box 2a, Folder 14)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2003-2004 (Box 2a, Folder 15)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2004-2005 (Box 2a, Folder 16)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2005-2006 (Box 2a, Folder 17)
  - Hearings and Trials, Abstracts, 2006-2007 (Box 2a, Folder 18)
- Series V: Constitutional Reforms, 1916-2004
  - "The Honor System of the Rice Institute," 31 March 1916 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Old Cases and Proposals, 1969- (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Appeals Reform, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee on the Honor Council, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Addendum of Suggested Blue Book Revisions, Fall 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Procedural Revisions, 1992-1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Procedural Revisions, 2000-2010 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Appeals Process Reform, Final Drafts, March 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Appeals Process Reform, Rough Drafts, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Appeals Process Reform, Notes and related correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - News Stories, honor trials of 22 Physics students and subsequent appeals process reform, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Honor trials of 22 Physics students and subsequent appeals process reform; communication with past chairs/officers (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Appeals Process Reform, Student Assoc. Constitution, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Appeals Process Reform, request for approval from assistant dean, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Appeals Process Reform, HC member opinion on Gillis' initial response to proposal, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Appeals Process Reform, HC member responses to Patty's Thresher comments, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Appeals Process Reform, HC member poll on final amendment draft, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Appeals Process Reform, Interpretation of HC member changeover, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chair's Report to the President on the State of the Honor System, 17 April 2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series VI: General, 1940-2005
  - General Information, 1990-2005 (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General Information, 1990-2005 (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Minutes of Meetings and Related Content, 1993- (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Accused, right to secrecy and an advisor, 1961, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Academic Integrity Conference, 1993-1994, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Faculty and the Honor Council, 1993- (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Orientation and Examinations, 1995- (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 2002-2004 (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 2002-2004 (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - News Stories, 1916- (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - News Stories, 1916- (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Honor Council Retreat (with case studies), 2002, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Surveys (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1940s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Honors Council Annual Report, 2016-2021 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Hearings and Trials abstracts, 2007-2008
  - 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 5)